The high tower loomed ahead of them, and with it, the final confrontation.
All right.
The final confrontation.
Let's see.
So, if we're going to get into the tower, do we have both keys now?
You have one of the two keys.
We have one of the keys.
LA is probably there waiting for Mozgoth to show up.
Okay, so he probably has the other one, and he's probably waiting for us.
So, or for somebody.
Ali Evanmore.
Well, I suspect this is going to be a fight.
Let me see whether there's whether I have anything to prepare.
Have we rested?
We have not rested, right?
No, you have not rested.
Do we have time for it?
You have a time for it.
Well, you can't know if you have time or you don't have time, but you can always take a short rest.
Do a short rest, at least.
Yeah, because I'm at nine hit points, so I think a short rest would be oh, I'm at full hit points, so I could use a short rest.
Yeah, it sounds like you being at nine is a you problem, but I'm kidding.
All right, I have completed my short rest, but it didn't
heal me.
Yeah, I don't always under the DD Beyond interface.
I don't understand it.
That one is just
here.
I'll roll it by hand.
I still didn't do it.
It's like broken.
Yeah, it's like this weird.
I can't figure it out.
Sorry, I say I'm doing a short rest.
I say I want to take, oh, I have to roll this.
So, my two-hit with Dawnbringer is now plus 10.
He don't.
You don't miss.
Yeah, she, he?
She.
They don't miss.
She, you know, Dawnbringer, you and Dawnbringer need to sort that out.
Like, I'm sorry.
I mean, you know, whateves.
Yeah, but you guys need to, you guys need to tell us what you guys want.
All right.
You know, her.
Dawnbringer is a she.
I have a girlfriend in high school named Dawn.
God help me.
Okay.
That's not right.
I told her to roll a whole bunch of dice.
How come I only rolled one?
You know what?
I'm just going to roll for everything, and I'm going to assume I got enough that I got my 45 that I needed.
All right.
Whatever.
I think that works.
All right.
Okay.
So you take a moment to rest.
All right.
Okay.
So Tadric hands you over the key, hands you over the key.
We got one key.
Yes.
Then as he hands it over to Key, it says, I held it all night and I didn't know what it was.
Now that I know what it is, I'm not giving it to you and going to bed.
He's offering to come along with you.
I assure him that he could be helpful, but it's also dangerous.
He goes, I faced, I faced Mozgoth.
I faced the full.
No, he's definitely suffering from a desperate desire to be heroic.
Well, come along.
I do have resurrection magic if worst comes to worst.
If Darrl was here, he says, but what about me?
Well, I didn't have it then.
Just as you're standing there, the acoustics deliver a sound from far off in the key.
The endless chant has stopped.
Now, one of the most important things about Candlekeep, just so you guys know, is that there's this endless chant of the prophecies.
Was this ever mentioned?
I don't remember this.
Yeah, I'm sorry.
If I never mentioned it, it was one of the things that I've seen.
I think I mentioned the first day that we were there, maybe.
Yeah, yeah.
So they continuously read the prophecies.
And every time a prophecy comes true, they delete the prophecy and keep repeating, right?
So if Grygum is anything like me, then I haven't noticed it for like the last three days anyway.
Once it stops, I notice that it stopped.
Yes.
But you also notice it because Tadric is kind of like stunned.
Like this is like, this never happens.
All right.
So now you have to decide.
So Tadric looks at you and says, Sylvyr, someone needs to tell Sylvyr that her son is dead.
He's looking at the four of you.
Well, there's this awkward silence as the four of you look at it, right?
It might best be someone who knows Sylvyr.
Ah, passing the buck.
I mean, go ahead.
We want to be empathetic, and like they would have the best understanding of how to be empathetic to her as they explain this unfortunate news.
And it's passing the buck.
It's passing the buck, right?
Tadric looks at the four of you.
So
you're just going to say, you know what?
Maybe later.
We've got to go deal with Ali Evanmore.
I'm happy to, you know, like back you up, but
I'll go with you.
It's okay, Daz.
You don't have to go.
It's fine.
I just want to make sure that Tadric kind of drops that bomb here.
Got it.
There you go.
Yep.
All right.
You guys decide sometimes.
Sometimes.
We'll take care of it later.
It's a later kind of problem, right?
Yeah, it's a later Emerald Vanguard or whatever we're calling ourselves these days.
Ember Grapple.
You're the Ember Grapple.
No causal or not.
No relationship between the two.
All right.
Okay.
So you've decided to, you'll go after the high tower to go see what's.
All right.
So Tadric fortunately knows where the high tower is, and he will take you towards there.
I was going to see if I wanted to prepare any spelling.
Let me see here.
Yeah, I will cast bless on the three of us who are here.
All right.
Okay.
That is not a bad decision.
All right.
As you approach, as you approach the, as you head towards the walkway, you notice a dead watcher.
Do you guys go on a little up ahead?
Do you want to go check out what's happened to him?
Watcher.
Yes.
That's the name of the guards of Candlekeep.
Does he look conspicuously out of place or that maybe he has some info?
No, he looks dead from an arrow.
Crossbow bolt.
Dead.
When you said dead, I thought.
Okay.
You thought he looked like dead?
So the arrow is out of place, maybe.
Yes, yes.
The arrow is out of place.
You look at the.
So do you want to investigate him or keep going?
Yeah, I think we spend a little bit of time investigating.
My passive investigation is now 24.
All right.
I don't know how that happened.
Just for the record, with a passive investigation of 24.
You're basically Sherlock Holmes at this point.
How did that happen?
Is that just from going up to level nine?
Now I'm curious, man.
I mean, this is one of the problems with D and D Beyond is: you're like, here's a number.
How did we get that number?
I don't know.
Sometimes it tells you, sometimes it doesn't.
We're going to complain about the user experience of this product.
No, no, I'm not complaining.
I got 24.
That's pretty cool.
Oh, is my intelligence is 20?
That would do it.
Yeah, I would do it.
Oh, did I actually get a stat and I didn't realize it?
And it just defaulted to intelligence.
That could be.
I don't know.
But I don't think you get that at level 9.
That would be.
So, no, your passive investigation is 24.
Oh, yes, yes, yes.
The way we're okay, so here's how it works.
So you see your investigation, which is a nine?
Yes.
And you see the plus five from intelligence?
Yes, those two add together.
Get 14.
Passive and get your passive number is equal to 10 plus.
Yes.
Right.
So your investigation is a plus nine.
Part of, and you have advantage when you roll.
Yes.
So I can figure shit out.
Yes, yes, yes.
It's like that Sherlock Holmes stuff where you can like he sees that the cabby didn't shave the back of his neck, and so he knows that his wife is dead.
Yes.
Because his wife would have told him that the back of his neck needed to shave.
Yes, basically.
Yeah.
Basically, we're basically at that level of investigation at 24.
Cool, cool.
Right?
You walk into a room, you see something, and you go, aha.
Aha.
Right.
So what do I aha about the arrow-ridden guard?
You aha.
I'm just going.
Right.
So now it's kind of like.
All right.
It's the crossbow bolt.
You immediately recognize the crossbow bolts fletching as not being from the area.
Okay.
Right.
And not being consistent with the crossbow bolts that are used by the watchers, which you had noticed as you had walked into the castle.
So clearly indicating that whoever fired this arrow came from outside of this cat of the candle keep.
Okay, so and knowing what we know, then that probably means it's outside actors that are up to all this mischief.
Yes.
Okay.
How it was fired from outside?
Are we on a wall?
Was it fired from below?
So it's on a walkway.
So he looks as if he was shot from.
So let me see if I can.
I need to draw.
This is going to.
This will not work well if I don't draw because I will get it wrong because my spatial reasoning is not like my wife's.
Natasha's spatial reasoning is kind of creepy.
Like she can't do 3D, but like if I draw, if she can navigate herself in an area where she's never been once.
No, my wife can't do 3D, but if you ask her, hey, will these leftovers fit in this thing?
She's always right.
Her volume estimation is amazing.
Okay.
Yeah, Natasha's of 2D spatial reasoning is kind of crazy.
Let me see my games.
Let me just get to the right game.
All right.
Ah!
Technology.
Why does technology exist?
Do you know why it exists to irritate me?
I've told you the whole why I hate technology.
It's because there's always some PM and there's always some engineering manager and there's always some engineer and there's always someone in QA and there's always somebody in UX and there's this thing that would make everybody's the customer's life better but engineering doesn't want to work on it.
The engineering manager doesn't want to deal with convincing people.
The PM doesn't think it's going to make more money.
The UX guy has this grand vision that they want to implement.
The QA person explains that it's going to, that the automation of it is going to take forever and customer support says there's a workaround.
Computers were a mistake, basically.
Yes.
And so as a result, they all turn to him and say, yeah.
And what they don't realize is he loves the workaround because it makes him the most valuable person in the room because he gets to drive up his customer, his customer sat numbers by saying this was a customer interaction that customer support nailed.
Everybody's got to have a reason to be there.
Yeah.
And that is why software sucks.
I just want.
And then I said this to a bunch of people in a meeting, and I kid you not, by the end of the meeting, we had made that decision.
Like, seriously?
All right.
So the way to think about it is that, okay, I'll do it this way.
Okay.
So you're this, can you guys see?
You should be able to see me drawing that right now.
Yeah.
I see a gray line.
Yes.
Okay.
So this is a walkway.
And you guys are coming down the walkway.
And as you are coming down the walkway, you see a dead watcher.
Am I supposed to see just sort of gray lines and squares, or is there something?
Yeah, yeah, that's it.
Okay, yeah.
So to make sure I'm not missing anything here.
No, no, you're not missing anything.
All right.
So this is the walkway.
Okay.
Are we indoors?
Yes, you're indoors.
So this is right.
So you came up some stairs.
All right.
So you climbed up some stairs.
Right.
It's quite unusual for someone to be killed with an arrow indoors.
Yes.
And so what you've concluded is that the bad guys went up the same stairs, killed him, and kept advancing forward.
The arrow was shot from the direction that we're coming from.
Yes.
Okay.
Right.
So I'll just to make this totally obvious.
Um, this is part over here.
All right.
So Edric goes over here.
Let me just make this to the map layer so that I don't map.
All right.
So
this is the direction everybody's going.
Consider this notional, not necessarily representational, to give you guys sort of a visual understanding of what's going on.
Okay.
Got it.
So I'm not like a medical expert or anything, but well, actually, I am.
I have plus five medicine.
How long ago do I think he was shot?
Not very long, like within the last half hour.
Okay.
So let's look out for somebody with a boat.
Yes.
You can.
All right.
So I presume you're now going to be walking a little bit more cautiously and not trying to make sure that preparing for anything is kind of the situation, right?
Cautiously, yeah.
Okay.
You arrive at the skyscrapers and there are two raiders looting the lobby, bagging books from a written manifest.
Skyscraping?
So that's the name of the lobby.
So if we go back to here, right, you arrive at the lobby.
Let me just draw this in a different color.
This is the lobby.
Okay.
Lobby of High Tower.
Oh, okay.
It's the entrance, basically, to this tower.
Okay.
And inside here, there are two raiders who are reading a manifest and pulling books.
I suppose they haven't noticed us yet.
No, they haven't noticed you yet.
When you say raiders, what do they tell me a little about them?
Well, they're guys in equipment.
They've got swords.
You look at them and you realize some of their swords have blood, right?
Okay.
And probably one of them has a bow.
Yeah.
Actually, that's the thing you notice.
Nobody does have a bow.
What you do here, though, is up the stairs that
make sure I got this.
All right.
As you look inside, so there's a guard here.
There's a couple of guards.
And then on the second floor of the landing is a wizard
whom you recognize.
Wait, this is somebody we can see from the lobby?
Are we past the line?
Yeah, I'm about to explain.
Yeah.
Okay.
Just wanted to
give me a second.
All right.
So as you arrive, so let's here we go.
Let's put him in the right layer.
Change layer.
All right.
So you guys arrive at the lobby.
And inside of the lobby of the high tower, so you're kind of at the near the top of this high tower.
You see two guards.
And there are two people sort of like pulling books and trying to like grab stuff from a sort of a list.
And then standing on the second floor of the landing is a wizard whom you recognize as Alay Ivanmore.
Oh, this is the guy who has the key.
Yes, this is the guy who has the key.
Did he need to use the key to get into the lobby?
No, he needed the key to get through the second door.
He is through the second door?
No, no, he's not through the second door.
Oh, okay.
So we have the other key, and presumably he does not.
Yes, I'm going to just draw that second door so that you guys know that.
So it's safe to assume that one of these people that's in front of us is one of the people that shot the guard.
Yes, yes, yes.
I should have made that was my mistake.
Yes, one of them does have.
Yes, one of them does have a bow.
Sorry.
Okay.
Well, that clears up a mystery.
Good.
Yes, yes.
So Alay Avonmore is sort of sitting over there.
He's waiting over there.
You guys see what's going on, but you haven't yet marched in.
So I'm going to give you an opportunity to decide what you want to do.
I'm more worried about the wizard than about these raiders.
We're probably more than a match for them.
Yes.
Just to put things in perspective, the Alay Avonmore is a pretty powerful wizard.
So keep that in mind.
But like all powerful wizards, he's also more obsessed with staying alive than he is fighting to the death.
Just like dragons.
Yes.
So is he the one with the third eye?
What do you mean, the third eye?
He's the yeah, yeah.
Let me just make sure that you.
I realized I wrote the name, but I didn't set it here.
You should be able to see him now.
Yeah?
Yes.
All right.
So yes.
It's a really awkward picture because he's supposed to look like a drow wizard, but you know.
He looks a little bit like a Hindu clown or something.
I don't know.
One thing we could do, guys, is try to eliminate the raiders so that we can focus on Alay.
So I could cast some kind of spell to try to get them in one spell casting.
Because I suspect that we just need to fight them and kill them.
How tall is the wizard?
He wasn't expecting that question.
He's...
Can we say between five feet and six feet?
Does it need a specific number?
Just less or more, more or less than five feet.
Between five and six feet.
Adult human height, I guess.
He's not under five feet.
I had a plan for maybe boxing, literally boxing the wizard in while we took care of the other guys, just to make sure we were clear.
But I think I'll wait on that.
Maybe use it for something else.
Yeah, I like the plan of just like knocking down the knock down the DPS towards us by getting the two weaker guys out of the way.
All right.
Excellent.
By the way, that road builder thing you sent me is pretty cool.
I did load it and it's working fine in my browser.
Great, great, great, great.
Yes, I got really annoyed.
And so I've been working on trying to, what's the word I'm looking for?
Trying to see what I can do with the stupider AMI models.
And so one of the things I did was use it to create those things.
It fought me that stupid AI models have learnt from really stupid programmers who don't, and so I had to beat it with a stick to tell it to stop trying to use regex to parse HTTP.
Ugh.
Or your HTML, you mean?
Yeah, HTML.
Oh, my God.
Like, it kept trying to do that.
I said, don't do that.
Finally, I was like, don't do that.
But you see, I'm so used to talking to junior engineers that I would say, like, please don't do that.
Can you not do that?
I really want you to not do that.
So, hold on, hold on.
So, finally, I said, can you write out the rule?
And the rule was like, don't worry that.
If you do that, you're doing something wrong.
I've been finding that I've been getting into these like rat holes with the agent where it's like, we'll start being super pedantic about stuff.
And instead of saying, why are we being so pedantic?
This is stupid.
I'll just continue to go down.
And so you end up with like the most bulletproof, like, well-specified bash script you've ever seen, right?
And at some point, I just have to like reel the thing back in and be like, we're being dumb here.
This shouldn't be this hard.
What the hell are you doing?
But you have to be able to say to yourself that quality is a variable that I'm willing to turn, a dial I'm willing to turn, which is hard to admit sometimes to yourself.
Yes.
Yes, it is.
All right.
So, all right.
So you want to take out the MOOCs?
All right.
So let's just do the lot led.
Then we will need a bit of a battle map here.
So let me just
do this.
Make page.
Ah!
All right.
Okay.
So I'll make it a tower.
Let me just see.
This is a pretty big tower.
There are some stairs over here.
Sorry, you're not seeing anything because I'm busily drawing.
I had a lot of things to do this week, so I didn't quite get all my maps done.
So I apologize for that.
Oh, you're fine.
It's fine, man.
I know.
It's, you know, my perfectionism is at play here.
Door over here.
Okay.
And then there is a passageway over here.
And okay, put some bookshelves over here.
All right.
Okay.
So, let me just see.
All right.
So, LA.
Draw mage.
Let's give him look a little bit more authentic.
Oh.
Okay.
All right.
I just, just so he looks a little bit more authentic.
Okay.
All right.
So you're standing at the doorway and the two guards are there.
I just need a few more seconds.
And there's some guards here.
Give me one more second.
I need to get the experience points out.
Is the mage Alay?
Yeah, yeah.
Let me just, let me just make sure that you guys have his name.
All right.
Alay is currently standing in front of the door, waiting, thinking that Mosey Quovo is going to run in at any point in time.
Well, he's going to be pretty surprised by us then.
Yes, guys.
All right.
So let's put some.
Give me one more second.
Okay.
All right.
So there are bugs.
Just to be clear, from where you are, you can't see everything in the room, right?
Well, that's code for the jam warning you that there may be other people in the room you can't currently see.
Uh-oh.
Just, you know.
Okay.
These guys are sort of like over here pulling at the bookshelves.
All right.
Alay is sitting there at the table.
He will notice you the minute you walk in just because he's like 10, 15 feet above.
These are stairs intended to be stairs.
I see him.
All right.
Okay, so it's meant to be like 7, 15 feet above.
What is the 15 number again?
Oh, the 15 feet?
Yeah, it's meant to be 15 feet.
Yeah, okay.
Height.
Cool.
Glabbagool says, is this where we use the flying spell?
So with the spells that I've got, I could get both the thugs if I could get at the end of a line of them, or I could target any one of the people in the room.
Like, they're not lined up for a good aim from the door, though.
So maybe I should aim for Alay instead, and then the others, the rest of us can work on the thugs.
Sounds good.
What do you think, guys?
So what was the plan again?
Target Alay instead of the thugs.
Who?
Me, you?
Me with my spell.
I'm assuming that I can get a spell off before everybody realizes that we're there.
Yeah, and I'm happy to sort of distract and try and kite the thugs a little bit.
So should I try to cast a spell then?
I was thinking guiding bolt toward toward Alay.
Okay, if you're going to try guiding bolt towards Alay?
Yes.
It has a 120-foot range.
I assume that I'm within good range.
All right.
You're going to try to surprise him?
Yeah.
All right.
You're going to have, all right, your stealth?
Oh, stealth.
16.
All right.
I'm going to declare that he is most definitely not expecting you to show up.
So he heard you running upstairs, so no particular thing.
His passive perception.
16.
No, he does not notice you.
All right, roll to hit.
Okay.
I sort of jumped the gun on that.
So I got a 13, which is lousy.
Oops.
Yes, but he is a wizard.
Not used to fighting.
Ah, but he does have mage armor, so the spell does not affect him.
Alay, all right, so let's okay.
Let's roll for initiative.
Like the rest of you can, you can, the rest of you can try to execute a surprise maneuver as well.
Okay.
So roll, let's roll for initiative as well.
Hold on, let me just bring up the initiative tracker.
All right.
Why do I have two Dazzes?
Daz, what did you roll?
20.
It should be in there.
Why do I have two of you?
I only see one.
Sorry, guys.
I got everybody's initiative very confused.
All right, I got 15.
All right, you got 15?
Yeah.
All right.
What was your initiative?
Zalthir's initiative is something ridiculous, obviously, because
that's how Gabe rolls.
Literally.
Boom, boom.
No, it doesn't.
Plus four.
Can I tell from with my investigation, my passive perception and investigation from where we're at?
Can I make a guess as to the intelligence saving throw modifier that the wizard may have?
Yes, because he's a very powerful wizard.
His intelligence would be a very.
What are you going to try to beat his intelligence?
I was going to try to cast something and he would have to roll a 17 on an intelligent save.
Yeah, he's got a.
You could see a powerful wizard from a mile away.
Right.
Right?
And I realize that anything that's an intelligent save with him is probably going to be an automatic pass on his face.
And so, you know, I'm going to.
Given your insane intelligence and investigation, plus nine.
It's plus nine.
Yes.
Mine's plus ten.
So now I'm feeling like maybe he's not the smartest one around.
He's the smartest guy in the room.
All right.
What's your roll an eight or better, which is a better than 50% chance.
I'll probably not cast that unless we get desperate.
All right.
So I'm sorry.
Daz, I don't know what your initiative is.
20.
It's in there.
Oh, wait, it disappeared.
Yes, I know, because I ran into some technical difficulties.
Mine's 13.
All right.
Yep, I got yours.
Don't worry about it.
Okay.
And I need to get this guy here.
And then I need to roll this guy here's initiative.
Let's go.
This guy.
What's his initiative?
All right.
So does that mean I get to go first?
19.
Hold on.
How many points?
Oh, I have two of those spells left.
Good.
Right.
All right.
Daz, you go first.
I'm going to cast Maximilian's earthen grasp on our friendly wizard to distract him while my party takes out the thugs.
So he needs to make a strength save of 17 or higher.
What spell?
You cast that spell.
All right.
I don't know this spell.
What does it do?
Yeah, he's used it before.
I choose a five-foot section of space, which I'm going to choose right in front of him or to the side of him.
Unoccupied space in the ground within the range of the target.
A medium hand made of compacted soil rises there and reaches one of the creatures you can see within five feet of it.
The target must make a strength saving throw on a failed save.
The target takes 2d6 bludgeoning damages and restrained for the spell's duration.
Well, that's fun.
All right.
And then further actions, I can have it crush him.
So he's going to try to counterspell it.
He can counter spell?
Yes, he can counterspell.
You can counterspell.
All right.
How do you counterspell?
I've never counterspelled.
Oh, it's a don't you have the third level counterspell spell?
Did I train that one?
Maybe I picked something else.
Is this like the nope card?
Yeah, yeah.
Maybe that's when I got fireball.
Fireball counterspell, it's kind of one of those.
Okay.
So what level spell is it is?
It is Maximilian's grasp.
It is a second level spell.
All right.
So he uses his reaction to counterspell it.
He's now been attacked.
All right.
So he has now been attacked by Daz and by Grygum.
Thorin, roll to see if you have stealth to attack.
So stealth.
No, you do not.
Wait, wait.
All right.
Oh, okay.
Right.
Sorry.
I just want to look at sort of like, if I don't, then I'm going to go after him and I may, but like.
No, no, no.
I'm just trying to do like I have to see if anybody gets to attack before he does.
That's what I'm trying to do.
So if you didn't get.
Well, I can do.
So that was an ability check, right?
Yes.
I can do.
Oh, you also have Bless.
Does Bless give you a plus one to because you just.
It says when you're in the middle of the plus one die four.
Yeah.
Oh, wait, plus one die four?
You didn't roll your blessed advantage when you did your attack.
Oh, gosh.
Well, let me see.
What?
No, that's not enough.
Well, I rolled it wrong.
Yep, also not enough.
Like, that is like a one in 56 chance.
I don't know, man.
Not my day.
On my original roll, I had a plus nine and I got a 13.
Right, okay.
Okay.
Grygum, Thorin, do you have anything to improve your.
While you're doing that, I'm going to go check what.
Okay, what do I have to get, do you think?
You would have to get a 14.
And I'm at 12.
Yes.
All right.
So I'm going to do I'm going to use one of my second wins, which I can do with Tactical Mind, which lets me add a 1d10 to it.
Fuck, motherfucker.
The 16th.
If the check still fails, the use of second win isn't expanded, so I didn't lose anything by that.
Okay.
All right.
But also, motherfucker.
Grygum, Zalthir.
I guess Zalthir's up.
All right.
Zalthir.
Does Zalthir?
Like, I'm so used to his.
I had to get two.
All right.
Let me see.
I just, I'm sorry.
I don't know all of his abilities.
All right.
Does he have anything with speed extra attack?
No.
Ah, but he does have other abilities which allow him, which could be convenient.
Ah!
However, Zalthir and Glabbagool show up over here.
And this is why everybody hates monks.
All right.
And he will now attack.
Okay.
I'm going to try my speakers again.
They were working badly earlier.
All right.
So he does attacks once, attacks a second time.
And what was the attack rules?
So he does 22 points of damage on him.
All right.
So he's at 77.
Okay.
All right.
Shall we begin?
Daz, you're up.
So what happened with my cast?
Did that work?
Your cast, your spell did not work.
Did it bounce back or anything?
I'm fine.
No, you're fine.
It just did not work.
It just didn't work.
Okay.
So now I get.
Yes.
Now you get to get.
Do I know how often he can do the counterspell thing?
Yes, once per turn.
So you can do it now.
You could probably do it.
But it probably takes one of his spell slots, right?
It takes one of his spell slots.
He can't use something else as a reaction.
Okay, well, then I'll go ahead and cast the same thing again.
I have one more spell slot for that available.
So boom.
Okay, so you're going to have him burn another third-level spell.
Now he has to think.
Oh, but you see, there's another advantage of that.
If he casts the spell, he can't cast another spell this turn.
He can only cast a cantrip.
There you go.
So he has to decide whether or not he wants to be entangled and 15 points of damage.
Or something else.
Or if he wants to avoid that and then cantrip me or do something else.
Okay.
Yes.
I mean, there's always a something else.
Think.
All right.
Okay.
Let me just go.
So let me just see.
What does he do?
Okay.
He will.
I need to check what his spells are.
That was not what I was anticipating you to do.
Well done.
I'm persistent.
I know.
All right.
So here's what he does.
So what he does is he casts.
All right.
So he will try his chance at the saving throw.
Okay.
He spectacularly fails the saving throw.
So he takes 15 points of damage.
Is that what I'm hearing?
15 points of damage, and he is now restrained.
All right.
So technically, what is it called?
He is.
Yeah, he's restrained for the duration of the spell.
Hold on.
Okay, so restrained creature speed and he can't move.
All right.
So every round, he can do another check to see if he can shake loose.
But that uses his action.
Yeah, I got it.
So here's what he does: he takes the damage because he's a man.
Actually, he's a drow, but you know, he's a male drow.
All right.
And then he uses Misty Step to go over here.
You're standing over there, right?
I'm right here, right?
Yes.
So he's he takes a mistake.
He's taking Misty Step.
He's restrained.
No, no, he can.
Restrain means your movement can't change.
What?
Yes.
Misty Step allows you.
I think you can.
Hmm.
Yes, you can use Wild West Trade.
It's a teleport, not a speed thing.
Yes.
But you did force him to burn one of his spells, so he can't cast a fireball, for example, or a lightning bolt.
Okay.
Right.
And so he took the damage, but now, well, I can still move the hand to him, I think.
Let me see how far I can move it when it's my turn again.
Yes, yes.
And he immediately has to decide who is he going to attack.
Right, so what happened?
Give me the summary.
So you restrained him with a hand that came out of the ground.
He took 15 points of bludgeoning damage, and then Misty stepped his ass to the other side of the room, which got him out of the hand.
So he wanted to avoid burning his spell.
No, avoid burning his spell, and we made him burn a spell anyways, right?
Yes, he had to burn a spell.
Yeah.
He had to decide which spell.
Like, it was either that or use a massive debt.
So now he's forced to use
his cantrips.
All right.
So he's going to use his arcane burst.
Can't trip.
It's arcane burst.
It's because that's how they change the spells.
All right.
Public.
So he misses Daz.
What's your armor class, Daz?
My armor class is 12.
It's not great.
I could only miss on a two and a one.
I just want you to know that.
What?
And you got a two or a one, right?
Yes.
All right.
And now he hits you with a second arcane burst.
And you take quite a bit of damage.
Takes 26 points of damage.
And then he turns on Zalthir and misses.
I think Zalthir's are.
What is it?
Arcane Brown.
Cast that many times.
The fifth edition Arc Mages were buffed to make them easier to play.
I see.
Right.
So they were changed.
They don't have the full flexibility of spells, but they have their.
But I thought you said he got one spell per turn and he already burned it.
It's his cantrip.
It's a cantrip.
Oh, this is a cantrip.
The arcane burst is a cantrip.
Okay.
Yeah.
Yes.
So he has other spells.
He can't cast those other spells.
These are considered cantrips.
Okay, gotcha.
If you want.
So, yes.
All right.
Just so that we're on the same page.
They are cantrips.
He does have spells, but he can't cast any of them.
All right.
Now, is this like this can't miss or?
No, no, I had to hit.
He missed one.
Oh, I see.
Okay.
Well, where is the to hit?
Yeah.
I rolled an 11 and a 16.
Oh, okay.
Okay.
Oh, I rolled an 11 and a 25, and then the 13.
I'm having a hard time reading these new things here because it says arcane burst range.
It says damage.
Oh, that says 13.
That rolls the damage for it.
Got it.
Okay.
Yes.
Right.
So if I click the damage.
The 13 was to hit, and then you roll damage if it hits.
Gotcha.
Yes.
Okay.
Ignore my damage.
I just pressed the button that was right there.
That's fine.
Oh, Zalthir is in fact hit.
So Zalthir takes
damage.
29 points of damage.
Ouch, goes Zalthir.
He's blessed, right?
So he takes time.
Yeah, what does bless get us?
I guess you plus 1d4.
Why don't you read the description?
Yeah.
1d4 to an attack roll or save.
Whenever a target makes an attack roll or a saving throw before the spell ends, the target adds 1d4 to the attack roller save.
For everyone, okay.
For each of the three of us, yeah.
But then after he does that, it says he stops.
Ah, all four and the boy Tadric, isn't it?
I'm genuinely glad I did not ask for him specifically.
He pauses.
You've been so thorough.
I want that on the record before anything else happens, because I don't expect either of us will have time for compliments in the moment.
Oh, I always have time for compliments.
He goes,
he goes, he pauses.
And then he says.
I mean, I also accept constructive criticism.
Do you want to ask him why he's doing anything?
Like, you're getting the impression that this is like that moment when the villain feels like he's.
Oh, sorry.
I'm just being a smart ass.
But why did you feel a need to kill everybody?
Is it just megalomania?
Are you trying to do that?
Daz, do you want to have your investigation tell everything?
Or do you want to let him say it so that you can fill in a few details that you've missed out?
Are you just trying to improve your impact factor in the journals?
He goes, you understand me.
Well, I was just trying to help somebody the other day get something into Arxiv, but I didn't know enough people who had credibility there.
All right.
He goes, he goes, you two?
For a moment, he's embracing, you know, Arxiv is now officially canonical a research community.
He goes, he pauses.
He stands up.
He goes, Janussi gave me 10 days.
Do you understand what he was offering me?
Mercy!
Genuinely, he thought 10 days was kind.
10 days for what?
I have been a Candlekeep for 31 years.
I do not have a house or a family or a country.
I have a chair.
He proposed to take the chair.
And I found, I was surprised at this, that I would do a great deal to keep it.
So this is just, this is the dude with the red stapler in office space, and he snapped.
Yes.
I didn't set out to be a murderer.
I didn't set out to be exiled.
I understand now.
You are going to lose your academic honor and privilege.
Right.
Exactly.
We should let this guy go.
It's all justified.
Thank you.
Does anybody want to ask why he's being
like, like, you know, is this all his plot?
I mean, like, he feels like he wants to.
You notice that there's books being stolen, right?
Like, this is kind of.
This is not a common monologue for a megalomaniac.
That's like, is this just like he wants to, like, somebody left him off of like a citation in a paper he wrote or something?
Like, he seems.
Oh, no, he's going to lose his chair.
Yeah, that's true.
So is there anything we can do to help you and to end this amicably without us needing to destroy you and your thugs here?
He goes, you keep saying I.
I want to accomplish that.
I want to correct that, not out of modesty.
I have been removing books from this library for 11 years, and I have never once chosen which ones.
A list arrives.
I fill it.
The courier who brings the list wears a glove on his right hand, and under the glove, the hand is metal, and I have never in 11 years worked up the nerve to ask why.
So who do you work for then?
His name is Manshoon.
You have not heard of it.
That is not an accident.
It is a career.
Manshoon?
Is this a multi-level marketing scheme?
Haven't people noticed the books are missing?
Do you have some copperware to sell us?
Yes, and so while you're kind of like going, roll a history check.
History.
22.
All right.
History.
21.
Apparently, I'm aware.
You immediately.
21 also.
All right.
With those kinds of history checks, you pause and go, but that's not possible.
You realize.
He's talking about the Zhentarim, the Moonsea, the man who owned Zhentil Keep, a wizard who has been dead more than once.
Well, if he's been dead more than once, then maybe he's going to be dead one more time.
After we're done with him, sure.
He goes, he then produces a sapphire.
Oh, is this a sapphire that you can break and the thing happens?
Yeah.
And he pauses.
He wants one book out of this keep, and he was always going to have it.
It was simply the version where nobody had to die.
He pauses for a minute.
It goes, as he looks around and realizes that Bookworm's dead, and Daryl almost died, and Janussi's dead.
And, you know, there's the guards who died.
And goes, well, fewer people had to die.
Fewer.
Yeah.
Right.
And then
he takes the sapphire and smashes it.
I was looking for a spell that I might have to grab that sort of thing.
I have telekinesis.
Do I have time, like, in a reaction to grab the thing from him and pull it to me?
It's a level five spell, so his whole anti-spell cast thing may run in some damage.
Oh, yeah, sure.
We'll do that.
Let's go for it.
All right.
I just casted it.
You are casting it.
All right.
So he rolls his.
So that's a 15.
He has to beat a 15 to.
Oh, he does not.
And now he's restrained again.
Oh, wait.
That's only if I'm holding on to him.
Yeah.
Never mind.
All right.
So you've cast the spell.
So I guess then we have to go through the whole damnation of order again.
Okay.
So you cast the spell.
He goes, all right, so.
Okay, so he has to do a strength saving throw.
And if he fails it, then I pull the object away.
All right.
You have the useful spell.
I wish I'd had something like that.
Good job.
What do I have to roll?
What is the strength check I have to roll?
Is that listed on here?
Why does it not say?
Well, it's whatever your spell DC.
This is what I'm reading.
For an object, you can try to move a huge or smaller object.
If the object isn't being worn or carried, blah, blah, blah.
Doesn't apply.
If the object is being worn or carried, I'm assuming it's being carried because he has it in his hand.
That creature must succeed on a strength saving throw, or you pull the object away and move it up to 30 feet in any direction within the spell's range.
All right.
Roll to so what's your spell DC?
Your spell DC is right above your spell attack rolls, right next to your attack roll.
Right next to my attack roll.
Attack spell DC.
It just says hit DC.
Scorching Ray is plus nine.
I don't know.
No, no, no.
If you go to spells, spells.
Okay.
Oh, spell attack is plus nine.
Thank you.
And the save DC is 17.
Yes, that's what I wanted to know.
I don't have one of those, but I don't have a lot of spells.
So you don't.
You can cast spells.
All I have is Lesser Restoration, which is the.
Oh, yeah, yeah.
Okay, so he gets.
So I think maybe it doesn't show me that then.
All right, so I have to roll it.
Okay, so you managed to wrench the artifact out of his hands.
Sweet.
All right.
And it's in my hand now.
Back to the turn order.
We are.
Back to what?
All right.
So, Daz, you just rolled telekinesis and grabbed it out of his hand just before he wanted to grab it.
It is now in your hands.
There are these.
There are still these two thugs over here.
So what I forget what the rule is.
If we break it, then it teleports somebody or teleports the key directly to my hand or something.
How does what?
I know we know it.
I just need to look it up, I guess.
Yeah, yeah.
That's the case.
But let me just make sure.
Yes.
Yes, that is.
And who has the other key right now?
Grygum?
Is that right?
Yes.
I've got it.
All right.
So you have the key.
It'll take another action for you to smash it.
So just keep that in mind.
Okay.
You can hand it over to somebody else who can smash it.
Like Thorin can smash it with a wave of his.
Actually, you don't actually have, like, you know, this is one of those awkward things where you can't smash things with Dawnbringer.
You could use the Hilt.
She wouldn't mind.
The expensive Hiltmaster 2000.
No, no, no.
That's the case.
I'm talking like Dawnbringer herself, right?
Right, right, right, right.
I'm just saying, like, if you have a sword and you want to crack a walnut, you can just like smash the bottom.
No, no, totally, totally, totally.
I'm just saying.
I once went to Renfair and discovered all the different ways in which a longsword could be used as a deadly weapon.
People think of the pointy sharp end as the dangerous parts.
There's like five different other ways in which you can be badly maimed with those things.
There's plenty of ways that you can get hurt just being careless.
Yeah, yeah.
No, absolutely.
Absolutely.
All right.
So, all right.
So, Daz, you have the gem in your hand.
I'm going to put a little circle on you so I know who has the gem.
All right.
Do you stand there or are you just going to run down the hallway?
So, what's the deal?
If I crush it, I get the other key.
You get whatever happens.
I get whatever happens.
You trigger something, but we don't necessarily know which.
We don't quite know which.
Okay, so I think what and I have let me check something for all we know.
It summons an elemental to kill us all.
Costatas is like, how'd you read?
Did you read ahead?
No, no, I'm okay.
I'm going to cast a cantrip for minor illusion.
And while I'm doing it, I'm flamboyant with my hand like I'm a fan of.
Oh, no, you can't.
You already cast a spell.
So you can't cast any more spells unless they're bonus action.
Damn it.
All right.
That's a full action.
What bonus action spells do I have?
I'm just double-checking.
I think you might be able to do cantrips.
I just tried to do a cantrip.
I can do Misty Step.
That's a bonus action.
Which actually is not necessarily a bad idea.
Yeah, it's the only bonus action spell.
You're going to run away with the key.
Is that the idea?
So I think what I'm going to do is I'm going to duck back into the hallway and make it look like I'm running away.
But I'm actually going to hand Grygum the thing, but I'm going to do it with like sleight of hand so that somebody watching me doesn't know.
I'm going to accidentally run into Grygum, but instead of pickpocketing him, actually make sure that he knows that he has the gem because he has the other key.
And that way, if the key shows up there, he'll have both.
Good idea.
Do I have to use my action to receive it?
No.
Yeah, I could just slip it in his pocket or something.
Yeah, you can, like, yeah, I mean, so taking the gem and like it's a free action.
Like, you can, like, trying to break it, smash it, like, do something more than other pass it around is a free action.
All right.
So I'm going to act like I moved over here, like I was running away with the thing, but Grygum actually has it.
That sounds like a sleight of hand check to me.
You're going to try to make it so that nobody notices?
Yeah, nobody notices because I rolled a 19 on my sleight of hand.
All right.
Okay.
So let me just make another note here that Grygum has the fake key.
Again.
And the real one.
No, no, no.
The fake sapphire.
Sorry.
Oh, okay.
I'm just like.
We already have the fake one.
What?
I know.
I give him the one I have.
Or is the one I have the fake one?
No.
No, no.
I was just being, I was making, I misspoke there, Mike.
Don't worry.
Okay, okay, cool.
I was just laughing at the fact that Grygum gave Daz the fake key earlier, and now Daz is faking the sapphire to Grygum.
Right, right.
I now have one key and one sapphire.
Yes, exactly.
All right.
Allay is very upset.
Good.
Keep away.
Even better.
Like, when they get upset, they make mistakes, and that's what we need.
All right.
I'm feeling pretty good that my lowly little wizardry here is keeping him pretty occupied.
No, no, this is very impressive.
This is very impressive.
Okay, it looks like it's a lay's turn now.
Yes, I'm trying to figure out what he's going to do.
This was not in all the things I had planned, right?
Can he do anything?
I thought he was.
Yeah, he can do things.
Yes.
He can't move.
He already spent a spell.
Oh, yeah, he spent his spell because he tried to control.
He's tried.
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
Because he did the Misty Step, right?
No, no, he did the counter spell to.
But wasn't Misty Step a spell too?
Yeah, that was the previous round.
Oh, sorry.
Okay.
Yeah, so I'm assuming we have the dialogue here, right?
And so Daz casts the spell.
Ale is sort of sitting over there.
He's now.
What is he looking?
Okay.
What is he going to do?
All right.
So Allay decides, steps over here and decides that he's going to.
He couldn't move.
Oh, no, no, he can move.
I didn't grapple him.
I grappled the thing.
If I grappled him, he would have been restrained.
Okay.
Yes.
Right.
So he decides he's a coward.
So he's casting a wall of force around himself.
Does he do that?
Or does he try to go.
He's kind of struggling with what he should do.
I can't cast Wall of Force because he just burned all of his.
He burned everything.
All right.
He looks at Zalthir and decides to attack Zalthir.
Oh my God.
I can't believe I rolled so poorly.
I rolled two ones.
I don't know whether you guys can see that.
I did.
Yeah, but I don't know what the four of them mean.
Is that damage or is that?
No, no, that's four attacks.
Oh, okay.
So he gets four attacks.
Looks like he got one.
Yes, you got two.
He got two, actually, because the plus nine and the 18 are the seven plus nine hits.
So that's definitely.
Wait, he gets four attacks that are plus nine.
Yeah.
He's pretty high level, I guess.
He's a very high-level wizard.
What level is he?
Who took that damage?
Zalthir just took Zalthir just got knocked out.
Oh, damn.
That's my bad.
I was a little bitch and grabbed the sapphire and ran away.
All right, so Zalthir is knocked out.
Fortunately, Gabe is not here to correct me with all of the caveats.
I'm sure he has some at this point in time.
At this point in time, I want, just for the historical record, Gabe would have figured out how to sleaze back himself out of this.
Yeah, if there's a saving throw, Bless helps.
No, there's not.
Okay.
So, and I like Avonmore kind of like tries to hide himself sort of behind the behind the bookshelf.
All right.
Thorin, you're up.
So there's these two thugs that are standing there ready to be terrifyingly intimidated.
Well, I know our original plan was that I was going to fight the thugs.
I don't think I can get.
That's a bookshelf, by the way.
Oh, so I'd have to go around and.
Yeah.
You could take an attack of opportunity.
There's nothing.
With that.
If you walk past them, yeah, it's like, I mean, I can do 30, and I don't think I have anything that'll get me moving faster than that.
So I think what I'm going to do is I'm going to try and actually just take out the thugs because I don't want them sort of creating chaos.
What do you guys think?
That's reasonable.
Yeah, I wish I could do something for Zalthir, but I don't think there's anything practically I can do from here.
I can help him after the fight.
Also, Glabbagool's on top of him, so Glabbagool could always help him.
Oh, all right.
So I'm going to move.
So you can stabilize him from dying.
So I'm going to move here, and then we're trying to bring Glabbagool has to go all ballistic.
21.
All right, that's a hit.
21 points of damage.
Oh, wait, no, that's against undead.
So it's 13 points of damage, I think.
All right.
Because it's not undead.
They're not undead, right?
No, no, they're not undead.
Very much not undead.
And then, wait, can I do something?
Can I just say something?
They improve the performance of the blood splatter.
I mean, I don't know whether you notice that whenever you cause damage, you see the funnel of blood pops up.
It's good that they focus on the important things.
Oh, dude, like, that's the important stuff.
Like, it's like customer love.
All right.
Wait, I want to figure out what I want to do next here.
Give me a second.
What do I have?
I can do.
I don't want to waste too much on these guys.
So
just trying to figure out if I want to do anything super special.
Okay, so I have a superiority die, which I can use for maneuvers.
And oh, and as you're looking at them, you realize that these guys work for the Zentarim.
Oh, okay.
Right.
The problem is that this page of abilities is so freaking long that it's hard to figure out what's what.
Yeah, my son says he wants the character trait where you optimize your character and then just press a button so you don't have to think what you're going to do in the middle of combat.
I know, right?
Okay.
I'm going to do a menacing attack.
All right.
Which gives me a
okay, so superiority dies, which are down here, which are where?
I don't even freaking know.
Where are they on this thing?
I'm scrolling around.
All right.
This give me a 1d8 that adds damage.
Right.
So three, another three.
And then dude has to beat a DC16.
He did.
Well, damn it.
Well, he's, you know, he's a thug.
Like, you know, he's a Zentarum thug.
Or DC16 wisdom.
Okay.
So.
All right.
That was your first attack.
You get two attacks.
Yeah, yeah.
I get another attack here.
Sap, I believe, is with it.
Gives you advantage on the second attack.
So another eight.
And then he gets disadvantage on his next attack.
Okay.
That's what it does.
All right.
Grygum, you're.
You need to be able to do like more attacks.
This is the thing.
It's like, I just, I don't miss, but also I need to be able to just pound.
Grygum.
Yeah.
So I am going to charge forward here and then cast Tasha's caustic brew attempting to hit both of the thugs.
Oh, both of the thugs.
Okay.
Go for it.
Roll for damage.
So let's see.
They need to get us a 17 dexterity save to avoid getting covered.
They blow both of their saving throws.
Okay, then at the start of each of their turns, until they scrape it off, they take 2x4 damage.
Oh, this is a concentration spell, so I think I have to end the blast.
We're going to be right back.
I'm going to hit the restroom.
Are we almost done?
Yeah, we're almost done.
This is a.
So roll for damage?
It starts, it's at the start of their turns.
Ah, the start of their turns.
All right, well, it is the start of their turn.
So 2d4 is worth of damage.
Ah, okay.
Then let me do that.
Eight on one of them.
He dies.
And two on the other.
All right.
And we will stop here.
Thank you guys.
And we will have.
Let me just make a note here.
I need to add a note here that we can drop off.
I just need to note that Glabbagool needs to go.
Ah, okay.
There's two bottles.
I will note that they're covered in acid.
Okay.
Thank you.
Take care.
It was fun.
Bye.
Wait.
So how's the house?